Heat. Heat. [music]
Good morning.
>> Good morning.
>> I'm looking for Paige.
>> Hello.
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Right around with Jack. Let me grab him
for you.
>> Okay. Excellent.
>> This is Jack, our head of tech
integration. So everything to do with
the car, the engineering of it,
converting it from like standard doctor
into the rally like race car, the 31 XR.
>> Thank you very much.
>> See you later.
>> How much do you know about the program
at the minute?
>> Actually quite low.
>> Nothing.
>> So um if we go back a little bit, the um
T2 has always been a real fundamental
category within W2RC and the D car. So
T2 has always been that productionbased
category. So begin to be a car that's in
production uh through a set of
regulations to then compete. Um over the
last let's say 2 years um we've been
working really closely with the FIA with
Toyota with other manufacturers [music]
to start looking at what the first is
all yours. You can pause
>> sure just shout if you need any [music]
go and have a comment while you do
>> it's all right I can do it all. It's all
good. Cheers m before we started talking
to it was a case of what what do we want
to do with defender? Is there anything
we can do with Defender in a motorsport
space? And and the answer is we have to
really go for for the Everest Delro
motorsport which is which is Dhakar.
It's the toughest event, right? Um and
that also comes with the opportunity to
be a W2RC world championship competitor.
Okay.
>> Um but at the time um it's fair to say
that the regulations didn't really fit
for modern vehicles. And this is a very
different vehicle concept to something
like the Toyota Land Cruiser. We've
[music] got a fully aluminium monog body
and then the the chassis and suspension
is mounted from the body. Whereas the
Toyota and the Land Cruiser and other
cars um the more traditional layout. So
you've got like a ladder frame and then
the body sits on the on the ladder frame
and the ladder frame does all the work
for the chassis. So [music] different
vehicle concept
>> and this started 2 years ago.
>> Two years ago and actually less than 2
years ago really is when we started out
but the rear very short very very short.
So we've gone from concept of what the
program could be to this whole setup
[music] in probably less than 18 months.
>> That's crazy.
>> Yeah. In engineering um it's around
about 50 people.
>> 50. Yeah. So if you look at um JLR
engineering, it it es and flows. So that
we get huge amount of support from our
engineers at JLR because a lot of this
car is still production. You know the
body the body shell we'll go through the
detail.
>> What are the percentage maybe 30 to 20?
>> No no no by weight it's about 65.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> So the body shell
>> is standard. It's built in Nitra in
Slovakia where all every defender on the
road.
>> It has to be stock.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Yeah. You can make some modifications.
thing simple things like where there may
be a bracket to hold a piece of trim
panel on the production car you can take
that bracket off. Okay.
>> So we do all of those modifications on
the line and nera that's where all the
fenders are built. [music] So the body
shell starts it life in exactly the same
way as every other defender you see
driving. So then they come to to us and
they're handbuilt. So uh the rest of the
vehicle the body shell is is stock is
let's use the term stock cuz it works.
>> Um the engine is stock the gearbox is
stock. uh the transfer case that does
all the four-wheel drive distribution is
stock, the subframes are stock with some
reinforcement. Um and then that's where
we start to do the rally engineering.
That's where we start to engineer for
for the environment. That's the way the
regulations are built. Mandates that you
keep the let's call it like the
fundamental architecture of the car.
>> So the body shell engine drive
>> concept and we also have to keep
something called the kinematic principle
which is the way that the suspension
arms are mounted to the inboard of the
body. we can change the outboard,
>> but the suspension principles really
governed by the inboard mounting. So,
yeah, that's that's the package that
we're working to. I mean, arguably, I I
think it's the [music] case that that's
a harder engineering challenge than
building a prototype vehicle from
scratch, you know, because you can
engineer it exactly the way you want,
whereas we have to start with a
production car,
>> find the limits of those systems, and
then engineer them to work in this
environment. So, it's been a it's been a
really interesting project. It's just
all about collaboration because we've
got a great team with our technical
partner Pro Drive.
>> The part of Pro Drive.
>> Yeah.
>> So, is it just here or it's also
engineering?
>> Engineering as well.
>> So, if you think that you've got to
bring two big teams together, you need
to bring a team that know um how to go
to a rally raid event and build a rally
raid car
>> and then you need the team that designed
[music] developed defender.
>> Okay. And those are the the two teams
that come together. And my my team is
kind of the bridge between the two.
Finding out how we engineer the
production systems for this environment
and then bringing that to life with the
bespoke systems that we've built [music]
to to bring the D7XR ready to race.
>> Which one's the most difficult part to
engineer?
>> Uh it's a good question. There's been a
few big challenges. Um software is one
of the biggest challenges.
>> Come on.
>> Yeah. because the cuz [music] the car um
the Octa is is a really really capable
car and it's got huge amount of
bandwidth of capability and a lot of
that is supported by really complex
software systems. [music] We need to
simplify that but also keep all the
systems happy. So if you think about the
way this car is laid out the engine, the
transmission, [music] the transfer case,
the rear diff and the front diff are all
mechanically connected.
>> So if we want to put an installation in
like this car has got like a hydraulic
handbrake where [music] we can
mechanically lock the rear axle that is
that rear axle is linked all the way
through to the engine permanently. So we
have to be able to in software [music]
make the gearbox and the engine think
when the rear axle's locked to release
the torque. Otherwise we end up damaging
the [music] systems ourselves. Right. So
it's little bits like that trying to
make a production car that's designed
for the road and customer use be able to
survive the demands that it needs to be
a rally car.
>> Yeah. Can you tell us about
specification [music]
maybe horsepower?
>> Yeah, sure. So way so the the
regulations define all of that. So stock
regs are there's a few fundamental
principles. First is your base
somigation car. The rally car is born
from you have to make 1,000 units at
least over a 12 month period. So for us
that's the defender octa [snorts]
>> only octa counts not the standard ones
>> only octa. Well we we can select so
because octa already has a wider track
width different kinematics it's already
got the big V8 engine that's the right
car for us to start from and also it's
the halo product
>> and I guess to build the octa was on
purpose because of the rally.
>> No no octa was octa was first. So Octa
is our the most capable Defender ever
built and it is Halo product for
Defender at Land Ro and it's [music]
already it's got the V8 engine. It's got
the 60 kinematic suspension. It's got
amazing capability both off-road and
onroad. Then we asked the question now
how do we bring Octa into a rally car.
So the Octa was born before the rally
car. Okay. Yeah. [music] But the rally
program isn't just Octa. The rally
program is Defender. It's the motorsport
halo for all of our Defender brand. So
that's the first portion of the race.
Thousand cars over 12 months. tick that
box easily with auto production. The
second is that uh we're governed by a
power toweight ratio. So all of the
cars, any car that enters stock [music]
category is governed by 6.5 kg per
horsepower. So if you have let's say you
have a 2 and 1 half ton car, it works
[music] out to around about 400
horsepower. We're homologated now. Our
homologation weight is published on the
FIA website. Uh just under 2 and 1/2
tons. Yeah.
>> Ben, this is Gus. So Gus is our program
director at Pro Drive.
>> Gus and I work together, manage the
team. invest pro drive side me JLR
motorsport side and we yeah put [music]
all the right pieces together the right
people together to do the car and all
the infrastructure around it you can see
that it's a defender right got an octa
nose and the [music] reason that it's
got an octa nose is two two form the
design of this car was done by our
creative team at JLR the guys that
designed [music] defender and are
designing the new defender and design
all of our rovers but the regulations
also say that [music] we can't change
this
>> oh okay
>> so we can't put a new bumper on the car
what we can do is chop the bumper to
improve the approach angle which we've
done only slightly when you look at the
octa [music] it's only about this this
much has been cut off and then we
replace the geometry of the nose with
the bash guard.
>> So that's mean so all of this is between
6 and 10 [music] mil aluminium
underneath the car. These features are
all defender features that we've built
into the bash guard to give the car the
really distinctive nose that everyone
knows. You look at it and go it's also
[music] a design element.
>> Yes, exactly. It's a design element. All
of the um underfloor structure has
become part of the design of the car. So
then behind here is the first part where
it gets to a bespoke rally unit which is
our cooling system. So the engine
itself, all that [music] you can see
under here is a stock engine. It's
exactly the same. If you lift the bonnet
on Oxa, it looks exactly the same. Yeah,
it's our V engine. So it's a twin turbo
V8. Turbos sit [music] in the middle.
Air boxes are all stock. All that we've
done is fit underneath here a restrictor
>> and the restrictor is from the FIA and
that governs the powers, the weight
ratio. Where it gets unique is this
section here. So this is the main
cooling. All of this is bespoke for the
rally car.
>> Okay. Because we're in high ambient,
high demand on the car, really high um
thermal uh inertia running through the
vehicle, we need that unique cooling
pack and we drive it with fans.
>> Yeah. So, you are not allowed to put
this in the back?
>> No.
>> The regs are written to say it has to
remain in the location of the road.
>> Yeah. Is it a challenge to protect it?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, it is.
>> So, you can see the protection that
we've got. So, we've got kind of two
grills. We've got the big bash guard is
doing a lot of protection and what we're
trying to do is get as much air flow
through this radiator as possible. Uh,
but make sure that we're not overheating
the next part of the drive line, which
is the transmission. This engine's
really hot. We need to be able to pull
the air back out before it gets to the
transmission. Yeah. So, that's why the
venting in the bonnet. The bonnet looks
stock underneath. If [music] you pull it
down, you can see all the exits. They
come through and the air paths are back
up through the bonnet through each of
these exits here. And this nose exit
creates a level of negative pressure
over the bonnet. Pulls the [music]
position.
>> That's interesting. Oh, okay. So, the
air comes like this and makes a
>> Yeah, it's just a negative negative. The
idea is to pull the air out of the
engine before it gets to the
transmission. This car lived in the
virtual world before it lived in the
physical world. So we're doing a lot of
work in CE driven tools. So CFDCA try
and understand the limits of the
production hardware. We have a lot of
information about that from JLR. And
then we need to bring together the teams
the rally specific engineering to say
okay where do we need to find those
limits and what do we need to do to
engineer for them.
>> So this is a stock component. All of
this is as it is in defender. By
regulation we can give it some support.
So we bring the cage forward. We put a
stay across the the bonnet. The dampers
are mounted directly into into here
underneath. If you look under the
corner, you know, we talked about the
kinematic principle. [music]
So all the mounting positions, top arm,
forward, lower arm, and the lateral arm
are in exactly the same place as the
[music] road car. We have just
re-engineered them for the specifics of
this environment to be able to withstand
impact and give us some more rally
specific durability. And then we've got
a Billstein Blackhawk damper. We
partnered with Billstein. Billstein are
a partner and supplier to JLR um across
all of our Defender vehicles and wider
Land Rover.
>> So we've had a great existing
relationship with Billstein and this is
a really good opportunity for them to
demonstrate [music] their technology
outside of production and more of this
>> but they also develop further.
>> You've got it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So it's [music] a Blackhawk
system um compression rebound damping
hydraulic bump and rebound stops. Really
really capable unit and we've done a lot
of development. So that's just the
external reservoir. So that's where the
oil lives and all the settings.
>> A massive protection.
>> Uh it's a it's a reservoir. So it's
where the oil comes through.
>> I mean the the outside
>> Oh, the outside is protective. [music]
>> It looks massive.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's big. And obviously it's
quite a thermal challenge to to keep the
dampers [music] cool.
>> Yeah. So that's the corner. Combined
with that is a brake package. That's
again a rally specific grade package.
And we've got hydraulic braking,
hydraulic steering as well. It's the big
challenges.
>> Pistle exhaust notes.
>> Yeah. These are all unique. So these are
fabricated uprights. But if you look at
the geometry of them and you looked at a
Defender one, very similar. All we've
changed is the way they go together. So
we've now got a multi-piece upright. So
if we break one part, we just replace
one part. We don't
>> Do you have plans to bring something
back from the rally car into Octa?
>> We have plans not into Octa, but into
possibly another vehicle.
>> Okay. Okay. Well,
>> call this part one.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. So moving backwards, you can't see
it, is the transmission. The
transmission is exactly the same as the
transmission in in Octa. And actually is
the transmission in all the [music]
Defenders you can see driving around.
It's a ZF 8-speed transmission. What
we've done is redesign software in
collaboration with ZF. They worked
really closely with us and with the
teams at JLR. So we split the work
between the three organizations to
[music] develop that new software. And
there's lots of functionality as we
discussed like your handbrake
functionality, wheels free
functionality.
>> And if you work together, is it
physically on the same building or is
there spread around the country?
>> It varies. So Jarmine Pro are very very
close. So they're in Bambbury, we're in
Gaden. So we work really close with the
teams there. And that's really
fundamental to make this project go as
quickly [music] as we have. Um and then
when we work with suppliers like ZF, a
lot of it is done um virtually between
Germany
>> Germany and we come together to go
testing.
>> So they'll always be with us on test
whether that's Dubai, Morocco, in the
UK, in Wales, wherever we go, we'll
always have some support.
>> Do you know how many hours of testing
[music] you did?
>> I can give you in kilometers. So we've
done we've done just over 6,000 km of
test and that's combined [music] from
what we call mule car testing. So early
early prototypes all the way through to
rally car [music] test. And the first
prototype we built was in February,
March time last year. Then we built a
second one in May. Then we built the
first rally car in August.
>> So it was a rally to test [music] it.
Yeah.
>> We finished testing in Dubai. We did
Dubai Baja in November. And now we're in
crazy rest of the drive line. One of the
biggest changes that we've made is the
front and rear diffs.
>> So on a production [music] car, we have
an electronically controlled rear diff
and an open front diff. We've now got
mechanical limited split differentials.
>> Okay. Both front and rear.
>> Okay. So simplification.
>> Yeah. I have this in my Defender as well
at home.
>> Yeah. Yeah. In your old Defender.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it's going back to that kind of
mechanical controls. Yeah. Okay. So, no
no [music] electronic control on the
split from left to right.
>> Pop shafts are stock. They're all the
same. And then the half shafts are are
unique because of the increase in
torque, but we've got a 35 in [music]
wheel and tire package. Much bigger
rolling radius, bigger torque through
the axle. We've got a lower final drive
ratio. Again, all of that is just
building [music] more and more torque
stack. Um, and we need to be able to
protect the drive line for that. The
rear axle is where it gets really
interesting. Yeah.
>> So, by part of the regulations, we're
allowed to [music] make modification to
the body to mount the dampers. The
regulations are written, you're allowed
a maximum of two dampers per corner. So,
we've got to what we've done is [music]
we've created a new structure in the
back of the car to enhance the already
stiff fender body. Reason [music] being
that if you look forward here, you can
see the carbon fiber under floor for the
fuel tank. So, we have to take some
material out of the body to allow the
fuel tank to come through. We then
reinforce that with [music] some more
steel structure and that allows us to
mount the two dampers. Really
interestingly, this like we [music] say
the kinematics have to remain the same.
The inboard mounting of the lower arm
and the upper arm are all in exactly the
same position as the road car, which
means we've got the same suspension
layout as the road car. We've just
designed it to be wider and heavier,
stronger really. You can see the
suspension, the dampers are mounted on
different parts. So, normally your
dampers are mounted on the same part.
So, we've got the forward mount on the
upright and the rearwood mount is on the
lower arm.
>> And that's because the regulation allows
you to adjust this [music] mounting
point. Exactly. So, not the upper one,
but the lower one.
>> Yeah. They're both on the rear. We can
change the upper damper positions are
free.
>> The only bits that have to be the same
with the road car are the inboard
suspension bits. So, we can put the
dampers where we want.
>> But this position, this damper here,
it's in the same position as on the road
car.
>> Mhm. Okay.
>> Back of the car, you won't be a surprise
to you. Fuel tank, 550 L of fuel. It's a
really big fuel tank, but the fuel
[music] tank drops through the floor.
Then we've got a really nice design in
the middle that gives us extra capacity
for [music] the fuel, but also brings
the uh spare wheel and tires in. How
long does it take to replace? something
longer than in the T1 Plus. So, [music]
>> we actually did some tests yesterday.
Sarah and Sean drawn on his own. Um, did
it in just over a minute.
>> Wow. [music] Okay.
>> So, down the hydraulic jack is here. So,
activate hydraulic jack from the driver
[music] side. Har up, wheel off, wheel
on, wheel back in, ready to go in a
minute.
>> That's crazy.
>> I mean, that's without putting helmet
up.
>> That's it. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Really impressive.
>> So, you have two spare wheels, I guess.
Three. An additional one in the back
here.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Fuel tanks as central and as low
in the car as we can get it because of
the weight. [music] give us the mass
balance.
>> Are they any double pump just for
security reason that one is failing?
>> Yes, FuelTech has auxiliary and the
primary and pumps. Yeah. And what we've
got here which is quite a nice little
thing to talk about is [music] this is
all the compressed air for the tire
inflation.
>> But that tank the air suspension tank
from any Defender you drive. Okay.
>> So that that normally drives your
suspension up and down on your already
in the already there. It's in the
factory. Just use it. Just use it. Yeah.
>> Okay.
additional jack, sand shovel, additional
spare wheel, cooling channels, driver
[music] water, the helmet bags,
utilizing the space as best we can
without putting weight up height really
is the is the name of the game in the
back.
>> Quite different compared to a T1 Plus.
>> Very different.
>> Very very different. Yeah.
>> So you have plenty of space for
>> T1 [music] Plus is the chassis is
designed, the drivers are in it and then
just shrink wrap them in whereas this is
the body space is defined by the
casters. We'll look at the interior now
[music] and there's loads of space in
the interior.
What we've tried to do with the interior
design is very similar to what we've
[music] done with the exterior design,
and that's keep Defender look and feel.
So, if you look at these graph patterns
here, yes, they're done in carbon fiber,
but they're exactly the same joined into
your Defender. Same with the [music]
center console. So, we've got what we
call a hockey stick. So, in Defender,
the hockey stick is a really fundamental
part of the way the interior feels. And
we've kept that same with the hydraulic
handbrake. It's [music] in the same
position as the shifter. The production
vents,
>> the dash is unique, but the production
vents are kept. All the all the air
conditioning is done by the same unit
that's in the road car. You know, we
talked about that 65%. [music] A lot of
this is contributing to that. So, we try
and use the production components where
we can, even if the regulations tell us
we don't have to. Okay.
>> Because it's the best thing to do. So,
air conditioning is one of them.
Steering column is all the same. You can
see all the all the switch gear is
[music] all Defender switch gear. Yeah.
Yeah. And we've also done some really
nice interior touches like all the bags.
these bags for holding parts and tools,
everything the drivers and co-drivers
need. All of these were designed by our
interior design team, Jaguar Land Rover.
So, we're trying to bring everyone
together to make sure that we don't lose
the assets of Defender. [music] That's
the point.
>> Is there a story about the the design?
>> Yeah. So, I don't know the specifics,
but it's our desert geo palette for
Defender. So, it's a series of colors
that was defined by each environment
that Defender exists in. Okay.
>> So, the desert geop palette is part of
our overall design language for
Defender, and then you get the splash of
color with the roof. One of the biggest
changes we made from an engine point of
view, all the calibrations are unique.
Car's running on sustainable fuel, so it
runs on a 100% sustainable fuel and then
we've just managed the calibrations
around that fuel. [music] You'll notice
underneath here as well, there's a
rather big side exit exhaust.
>> So that means you bring your own fuel
here to Saudi and it stays
refueling area. Yeah. Yeah. If you look
underneath here, side exit exhaust.
>> All right. Yeah.
>> There's two reasons for that really.
There's the fact that it's really cool.
We love it. It's great. And also it
moves the exhaust out of the way of any
impact. So if you run the exhaust end to
end of the vehicle, [music] you've got
what 2 and 1 half 3 m of exhaust pipe
that any impact you could be crushing
that pipe and it affects the engine
before. So we just get it out as quick
as we can. That combined with all the
underlo protection. So big [music] sills
stills are there to help with rock
sliding and also protect the rear axle
and also you've got all of the underlo
uh trays. [music] They're about between
6 and 10 mil aluminium. What's the part
where you're most proud of but nobody
will see it?
>> Oo the like I said that software.
>> The software complexity of it. It's a
real difficult challenge because you've
got a complicated set of requirements,
but you need to simplify it. So, I'm not
a software developer, but there are some
amazing people in our team that have
been able to bring the software of this
car to life and, you know, make it think
and also just controlling [music] that,
driving the systems and mechanically.
What we've been able to do with the
Defender platform really shows how good
the car is. The suspension is
kinematically the same. It's just
stronger and and simplified again. So,
all [music] of those systems trying to
make them fit for this environment is
where we're all very proud of. I think
overall we're very proud of this car.
It's really difficult to try and pull
one thing out.
>> And what is pain point where you have to
deal almost every day? Let's call it
management of the environment. So the
car is incredibly capable,
>> but it's still a road car. Still got a
nose and a and a tail that make it
difficult for breakover angles over big
jeans. It's managing the production
parts of the car to make it survive and
make it performant environment. We've
done it through testing and this is this
is where it gets a bit serious.
>> All right, cool. Hey, thank you very
much. Really interesting. Have a nice
day. Me too. Thank you. Thank you very
much.
>> Thank you.
>> See you later.
>> Perfect.
>> Thank you very much. Appreciate
>> it.